Guide to the Bayrd Still Papers MC.44
New York University Archives
- Series III: NYC Research, 1650-1989
  - Subseries C: Sources about Urbanism and Urban Development
    - Buckingham, J. S., AMERICA, HISTORICAL,STATISTIC, AND DESCRIPTIVE, Describes cities, 1837-1840, undated (Box 30, Folder 50)
    - Barnard, Daniel D., Lecture on Commerce pro-city, 1838, undated (Box 30, Folder 51)
    - DEMOCRATIC REVIEW, Attitudes toward city, 1838-1840, undated (Box 30, Folder 52)
    - Neal, Joseph C., CHARCOAL SKETCHES; OR, SCENES IN A METROPOLIS,1838, undated (Box 30, Folder 53)
    - DEMOCRATIC REVIEW, Pro-rural view, 1839, undated (Box 30, Folder 54)
    - Narrative of a Tour to, & one year's residence in "Edensburgh," (Illinois). By Major Walter Wilkey. New-York, 1839. Satire., undated (Box 30, Folder 55)
    - "Progress of the Northwest," Hunt's MERCHANT'S MAGAZINE,1840, undated (Box 30, Folder 56)
    - New York-Philadelphia, Population rivalry, 1790-1840, undated (Box 30, Folder 57)
    - New-York and Albany Railroad Co., Boston-New York rivalry, undated (Box 31, Folder 1)
      3 1142 04225079 8
    - Trend to towns, 1840, undated (Box 31, Folder 2)
    - Buckingham, J. S., EASTERN AND WESTERN STATES OF AMERICA, Description of cities, 1842, undated (Box 31, Folder 3)
    - Response to Cities in Commercial Magazines, 1840-1860, undated (Box 31, Folder 4)
    - Bibliography of Periodical Articles, ca. 1850-1915, Reflecting Popular Attitudes toward City Growth, undated (Box 31, Folder 5)
    - Scott, Jesup W., "Internal Trade of the U.S.," 1843, undated (Box 31, Folder 6)
    - Chickering, Jesse, "Cities and Towns in U.S.," 1844, 1845, undated (Box 31, Folder 7)
    - Payne, Buckner H., "Contests for the Trade of the Mississippi Valley," 1847, undated (Box 31, Folder 8)
    - Poe, Edgar A., DOINGS OF GOTHAM, 1844, undated (Box 31, Folder 9)
    - Peabody, O. W., Review of [Anon.], ALIDA; OR TOWN AND COUNTRY, Pro-urban view of anti-urban work, 1844, undated (Box 31, Folder 10)
    - Von Raumer, F. L. G., AMERICA AND THE AMERICAN PEOPLE, Concern with cities in U.S., 1844, undated (Box 31, Folder 11)
    - Townsite speculation, AMERICAN REVIEW, 1845, undated (Box 31, Folder 12)
    - Land speculation in Chicago, 1848, undated (Box 31, Folder 13)
    - Tenement Conditions in Cities, 1845, undated (Box 31, Folder 14)
    - City Description in Books and Magazines, 1840's and 1850's, undated (Box 31, Folder 15)
    - Sensational Treatment of Cities, 1840's and 1850's, undated (Box 31, Folder 16)
    - Skilman, W. D., THE WESTERN METROPOLIS; OR ST. LOUIS IN 1846, undated (Box 31, Folder 17)
    - Franco, Harry [Charles F. Briggs], THE TRIPPINGS OF TOM PEPPER, 1847, undated (Box 31, Folder 18)
    - Downing, Andrew J., RURAL ESSAYS, 1847-1851, undated (Box 31, Folder 19)
    - "The Physiognomy of Cities," AMERICAN REVIEW, September 1847, undated (Box 31, Folder 20)
    - Foster, Geo. G., NEW YORK IN SLICES, NEW YORK BY GASLIGHT, NEW YORK NAKED, 1848-1850's, undated (Box 31, Folder 21)
    - Foster, Geo. G., PHILADELPHIA IN SLICES,1848, undated (Box 31, Folder 22)
    - [Baker, Benjamin A.], A GLANCE AT NEW NEW YORK, drama, 1848, undated (Box 31, Folder 23)
    - Buntline, Ned [E. Z. C. Judson], MYSTERIES AND MISERIES OF NEW YORK, undated (Box 31, Folder 24)
    - B'hoys and G'hals of New York, Mose and Lize, 1849-1850, undated (Box 31, Folder 25)
    - Wierzbieki, F. P., CALIFORNIA AS IT IS (San Francisco), 1849, undated (Box 31, Folder 26)
    - Dillon, Patricia, San Francisco, 1849, undated (Box 31, Folder 27)
    - Fisher, Ellwood, "The North and the South," DE BOW'S REVIEW, 1849, undated (Box 31, Folder 28)
    - Foster, Geo. G., "Immigrants," 1849, undated (Box 31, Folder 29)
    - Foster, Geo. G., "Newsboys," 1849, undated (Box 31, Folder 30)
    - SPIRIT OF THE AGE, August 1849, undated (Box 31, Folder 31)
    - "The City and the Country," PRAIRIE FARMER, August 1849, undated (Box 31, Folder 32)
    - Bremer, Fredrika, HOMES OF THE NEW WORLD, 1849-1851, undated (Box 31, Folder 33)
    - CITY CRIES; OR, A PEEP AT SCENES IN TOWN, 1850, undated (Box 31, Folder 34)
    - Koss, Milwaukee Germans, July 4, 1850, undated (Box 31, Folder 35)
    - Foster, Geo. G., Old Brewery and Five Points,1850, undated (Box 31, Folder 36)
    - Immigrants and City Growth, 1850's, undated (Box 31, Folder 37)
    - NORTH AMERICAN REVIEW, 1850's, undated (Box 31, Folder 38)
    - [Thomas P. Kettell], "Internal Transportation," Effect on urban life, undated (Box 31, Folder 39)
    - Urban Promise of U.S., ca. 1850, undated (Box 31, Folder 40)
    - Grattan, Thomas C., CIVILIZED AMERICA, ca. 1850, undated (Box 31, Folder 41)
    - Ross, WHAT I SAW IN NEW YORK (1851), anti-urban, undated (Box 31, Folder 42)
    - City Characters, 1851, undated (Box 31, Folder 43)
    - New York and Philadelphia Contrasted, 1851, undated (Box 31, Folder 44)
    - Anon., HERBERT TRACY; OR, THE TRIALS OF MERCANTILE LIFE, 1851, Anti-urban, undated (Box 31, Folder 45)
    - WESTERN JOURNAL, VII (1851) Civic Embellishment, undated (Box 31, Folder 46)
    - Philadelphia and Boston, Growth of Suburbs in, 1852, undated (Box 32, Folder 1)
      3 1142 04225078 0
    - Hawthorne, Nathaniel, THE BLITHEDALE ROMANCE, ca. 1852, 1958 (Box 32, Folder 2)
    - Melville, Herman, PIERRE, OR, THE AMBIGUITIES, ca. 1852, 1949 (Box 32, Folder 3)
    - St. Louis and New Orleans, Railroads, Manufacturing, 1852, undated (Box 32, Folder 4)
    - Olmsted, F. L., Blacks in Southern Cities, 1853, undated (Box 32, Folder 5)
    - Dix, John A., "The City of New York," 1853, undated (Box 32, Folder 6)
    - "New-York Daguerreotyped," PUTNAM'S MONTHLY, 1853 (Pro-urban), undated (Box 32, Folder 7)
    - Chambers, Wm., THINGS AS THEY ARE IN AMERICA, 1853, undated (Box 32, Folder 8)
    - Lossing, B. T., "Growth of Cities in the U.S.," 1853, undated (Box 32, Folder 9)
    - Phelps, [Humphrey], PHELPS' HUNDRED CITIES AND LARGE TOWNS OF AMERICA. Presumably first gazetteer to treat exclusively with cities., undated (Box 32, Folder 10)
    - Gerard, Jas. W., LONDON AND NEW YORK: THEIR CRIME AND POLICE, 1853, undated (Box 32, Folder 11)
    - Lathrop, John S., Reciprocal Interests of City and Farm, 1853, undated (Box 32, Folder 12)
    - Chapin, Rev. Edwin H., MORAL ASPECTS OF CITY LIFE, 1853, undated (Box 32, Folder 13)
    - AICP, FIRST REPORT OF A COMMITTEE ON THE SANITARY CONDITION OF THE LABORING CLASSES IN THE CITY OF NEW YORK, 1853, undated (Box 32, Folder 14)
    - St. Clair, Frank, SIX DAYS IN THE METROPOLIS, 1854, undated (Box 32, Folder 15)
    - Jones, John B., THE LIFE AND ADVENTURES OF A COUNTRY MERCHANT, 1854, undated (Box 32, Folder 16)
    - Robinson, Solon, HOT CORN, 1854, undated (Box 32, Folder 17)
    - Tucker, Geo., PROGRESS OF U.S. IN POPULATION AND WEALTH, 1855, undated (Box 32, Folder 18)
    - Foster, Vere, WORK AND WAGES, 1855(?), undated (Box 32, Folder 19)
    - "Great Cities," PUTNAM'S MONTHLY MAGAZINE, 1855, undated (Box 32, Folder 20)
    - "Chicago in 1856," PUTNAM'S MONTHLY MAGAZINE (June, 1856), undated (Box 32, Folder 21)
    - Bogen, D. W., German Immigrant Guide, 1855, undated (Box 32, Folder 22)
    - "Great Cities," PUTNAM'S MONTHLY MAGAZINE, 1855, undated (Box 32, Folder 23)
    - "Editor's Easy Chair," HARPER'S NEW MONTHLY MAGAZINE, 1855, undated (Box 32, Folder 24)
    - Beecher, H. W., EYES AND EARS (on Chicago), 1855, undated (Box 32, Folder 25)
    - Tappan, H. A., "The Growth of Cities," Lecture, 1855, undated (Box 32, Folder 26)
    - Cowley, Charles, A HANDBOOK OF BUSINESS IN LOWELL WITH A HISTORY OF THE CITY, 1856, undated (Box 32, Folder 27)
    - "Editor's Easy Chair," HARPER'S NEW MONTHLY MAGAZINE (1856), Landmark Destruction, undated (Box 32, Folder 28)
    - CITY SIGHTS FOR COUNTRY EYES, Picture book, 1856, undated (Box 32, Folder 29)
    - "Chicago in the Fifties," Growth of Western Cities, ca. 1856, undated (Box 32, Folder 30)
    - Helper, Hinton, COMPENDIUM OF THE IMPENDING CRISIS OF THE SOUTH, Need for Southern Metropolis, 1856, 1857, undated (Box 32, Folder 31)
    - Reaction of cities to sectional tension, 1856-1860, undated (Box 32, Folder 32)
    - Stirling, James, LETTERS FROM THE SLAVE STATES, Chicago described, 1856, undated (Box 32, Folder 33)
    - Tucker, Geo., HISTORY OF U.S., 1857, undated (Box 32, Folder 34)
    - Dana, C. W., THE GREAT WEST, City Growth, 1857, undated (Box 32, Folder 35)
    - City and Country, PUTNAM'S MONTHLY MAGAZINE, 1857, undated (Box 32, Folder 36)
    - Hundley, Daniel R., Reaction to Southern Cities, 1857, undated (Box 32, Folder 37)
    - Mackay, Charles, LIFE AND LIBERTY IN AMERICA, 1857, 1858, undated (Box 32, Folder 38)
    - Whitman, Walt, BROOKLYN DAILY TIMES, 1857, 1858, undated (Box 32, Folder 39)
    - DE BOW'S REVIEW, Urbanism of North a cause of sectional tension, 1857-1861, undated (Box 32, Folder 40)
    - Spalding, C. C., ANNALS OF THE CITY OF KANSAS CITY, 1858, undated (Box 32, Folder 41)
    - ATLANTIC MONTHLY, Lack of appeal of farming in New England, 1858, undated (Box 32, Folder 42)
    - Residential Architecture in Cleveland, 1858, undated (Box 32, Folder 43)
    - Washington, D.C., DE BOW'S REVIEW, Cities rationalized, 1858, undated (Box 32, Folder 44)
    - "Virginia and the Chesapeake Bay," DE BOW'S REVIEW, Argument for building up Norfolk as Southern rival for New York, 1858, undated (Box 32, Folder 45)
    - "The Rush to Our Great Cities," DE BOW'S REVIEW, Anti-urban view, 1858, undated (Box 32, Folder 46)
    - Fire Department, 1858-1865, undated (Box 32, Folder 47)
    - [Maurice A. Richter] THE MUNICIPALIST, Inter-city relations, 2nd ed., 1859, undated (Box 32, Folder 48)
    - Fisher, S.G., "Diary," Horsecars in Philadelphia; Suburban development, 1859, undated (Box 32, Folder 49)
    - Horsecars, Philadelphia, New York, Brooklyn, 1859, undated (Box 32, Folder 50)
    - "Manufactures of Paterson, N.J.," SCIENTIFIC AMERICAN, 1859, undated (Box 32, Folder 51)
    - Halliday, Rev. Samuel, Life Among the Poor, 1859, undated (Box 32, Folder 52)
    - Mayo, Rev. Henry, SYMBOLS OF CAPITAL; OR, CIVILIZATION IN NEW YORK, 1859, undated (Box 32, Folder 53)
    - Westward the Star of Empire, DE BOW'S REVIEW, City growth in Upper Midwest, 1859, undated (Box 32, Folder 54)
    - New Orleans, Hotels, late 1850's, undated (Box 32, Folder 55)
    - "Country Life," HARPER'S NEW MONTHLY MAGAZINE, 1859, Argues merits of both city and country, undated (Box 32, Folder 56)
    - Cist, Charles, Sketches and Statistics of Cincinnati, 1859, undated (Box 32, Folder 57)
    - Relation of Press to Growth of Cities, 1859, undated (Box 32, Folder 58)
    - Taylor, Bayard, San Francisco, Growth by August, 1859, undated (Box 32, Folder 59)
    - THE DOLLAR NEWSPAPER, Philadelphia, 1859, City issues, undated (Box 32, Folder 60)
    - City Growth, Miscellaneous Commentary, 1859-1863, undated (Box 32, Folder 61)
    - Godey's Lady's Book, City and Country Rival Claims, undated (Box 32, Folder 62)
    - Browne, J. Ross, A PEEP AT WASHOE, ca. 1860, undated (Box 32, Folder 63)
    - Brace, Charles L., DANGEROUS CLASSES OF NEW YORK, 1860's, undated (Box 32, Folder 64)
    - City Growth as of 1860, Hunt's MERCHANTS' MAGAZINE, 1861, undated (Box 32, Folder 65)
    - Milburn, W.H., Growth of cities in Midwest by 1860, undated (Box 32, Folder 66)
    - Changes in country life in South, DE BOW'S REVIEW, 1860, undated (Box 32, Folder 67)
    - STRANGER'S GUIDE TO PHILADELPHIA, 1860, undated (Box 32, Folder 68)
    - Philadelphia Attitude to Foreign Born, 1860, 1900, New York and Philadelphia compared, undated (Box 32, Folder 69)
    - Apartment Houses Anticipated, LESLIE'S ILLUSTRATED NEWSPAPER, 1860, undated (Box 33, Folder 1)
      3 1142 04225077 2
    - DE BOW'S REVIEW, 1860 -- Baltimore, a potential means of freeing South of dependence on New York City, undated (Box 33, Folder 2)
    - Clean Cities, LESLIE'S ILLUSTRATED NEWSPAPER, 1860, undated (Box 33, Folder 3)
    - Trollope, Anthony, Comment on Comment on American Cities, 1861, undated (Box 33, Folder 4)
    - Alleged threat of Confederate Army to Northern cities, 1861, undated (Box 33, Folder 5)
    - Morford, Henry, DAYS OF SHODDY, Pro-urban sentiment, 1861, undated (Box 33, Folder 6)
    - Stewart, A. T. and Co., Astor Place store, 1862, undated (Box 33, Folder 7)
    - Bookwalter, John W., Civil War as cause of urban growth, 1863, undated (Box 33, Folder 8)
    - Civil War, effect on cities, 1863, undated (Box 33, Folder 9)
    - Campbell, John F., A SHORT AMERICAN TRAMP IN THE FALL OF 1864, undated (Box 33, Folder 10)
    - City and Country, 1864-1866, undated (Box 33, Folder 11)
    - Pro-city sentiment, LESLIE'S ILLUSTRATED WEEKLY, 1865, undated (Box 33, Folder 12)
    - Southern cities, Effect of Civil War on, ca. 1865, undated (Box 33, Folder 13)
    - [Kendall, Isaac C.], THE GROWTH OF NEW YORK, 1865, undated (Box 33, Folder 14)
    - Godkin, E. L., Influence of frontier, 1865, undated (Box 33, Folder 15)
    - Fifth Avenue Rentals, 1865, undated (Box 33, Folder 16)
    - Metropolitan Health Bill, 1865, undated (Box 33, Folder 17)
    - Dilke, Charles, Ethnic "complexion" of American cities, 1866, undated (Box 33, Folder 18)
    - Dilke, Charles, San Francisco, 1866, undated (Box 33, Folder 19)
    - [Parton, James], The Government of the City of New York, NORTH AMERICAN REVIEW, 1866, undated (Box 33, Folder 20)
    - Arguments for rapid transit, 1866, undated (Box 33, Folder 21)
    - "Future of Great Cities," NATION, 1866, undated (Box 33, Folder 22)
    - City and Country, 1866 to 1870, Whitman, Twain, et al, undated (Box 33, Folder 23)
    - Wealth in High Society; contrast with low society, 1860's, undated (Box 33, Folder 24)
    - City and Country, labor crisis, 1867, undated (Box 33, Folder 25)
    - Hale, Edward Everett, Reaction to cities, 1860's, 1870, undated (Box 33, Folder 26)
    - Department Stores, Philadelphia, Chicago, 1867, undated (Box 33, Folder 27)
    - "The Railroad System," NORTH AMERICAN REVIEW, 1867, undated (Box 33, Folder 28)
    - [Godkin, E. L.], "City and Country," NATION, September 26, 1867, undated (Box 33, Folder 29)
    - Union League Club, Report on Cities, ca. 1867, undated (Box 33, Folder 30)
    - Zincke, Foster B., LAST WINTER IN U.S., 1867, 1868, undated (Box 33, Folder 31)
    - Parton, James, Articles on Chicago, St. Louis, Cincinnati, Pittsburgh, ATLANTIC MONTHLY, 1867, 1868, undated (Box 33, Folder 32)
    - Browne, Junius H., THE GREAT METROPOLIS, 1867, 1868, undated (Box 33, Folder 33)
    - Adams, Charles F., Growth of Boston, NORTH AMERICAN REVIEW, 1868, undated (Box 33, Folder 34)
    - Smith, Mathew H., SUNSHINE AND SHADOW IN NEW YORK, published, 1868, undated (Box 33, Folder 35)
    - McCabe, Jas. D. [pseud.], [Edward Winslow Martin], SECRETS OF THE GREAT CITY, published, 1868., undated (Box 33, Folder 36)
    - Metropolitan Board of Health, Health, Annual Report, reviewed in NORTH AMERICAN REVIEW, 1868, undated (Box 33, Folder 37)
    - Alger, Horatio, RAGGED DICK; OR STREET LIFE IN NEW YORK WITH THE BOOTBLACKS, 1868, 1973 (Box 33, Folder 38)
    - "Life in Great Cities" series in PUTNAM'S MAGAZINE, new series. First issue contained article on New York, 1868, undated (Box 33, Folder 39)
    - Green, Andrew H., Need for city planning, 1868, undated (Box 33, Folder 40)
    - Olmsted, Vaux and Co., PRELIMINARY REPORT...SUBURBAN VILLAGE AT RIVERSIDE, NEAR CHICAGO, 1868, undated (Box 33, Folder 41)
    - Large Cities, Popular recognition of, 1868, 1869. See "Our Great Cities," NATION, 1869, undated (Box 33, Folder 42)
    - Whitman, Walt, 1868-72, including DEMOCRATIC VISTAS, undated (Box 33, Folder 43)
    - Wright, John S., CHICAGO: PAST, PRESENT, FUTURE, 1868-1870, undated (Box 33, Folder 44)
    - Beadle, J. H., THE UNDEVELOPED WEST, cities of the Great Plains, 1868-1873, undated (Box 33, Folder 45)
    - Estimate of New York City's Population Growth, 1868-1878, undated (Box 33, Folder 46)
    - Stevens, Geo. E., THE CITY OF CINCINNATI, Growth by 1869 conceived in organic terms, undated (Box 33, Folder 47)
    - "Go West, Young Man," NEW YORK WORLD, 1869, undated (Box 33, Folder 48)
    - Chicago's Suburbs, 1869. Reference to Crystal Lake, Woodstock, Ill., undated (Box 33, Folder 49)
    - Village Improvement Associations, Impetus to, 1869, undated (Box 33, Folder 50)
    - New York Association for Improving Condition of Poor, ANNUAL REPORT, 1869, undated (Box 33, Folder 51)
    - Municipal Administration, late 1860's, NORTH AMERICAN REVIEW, undated (Box 33, Folder 52)
    - Ellington, Geo., THE WOMEN OF NEW YORK, OR SOCIAL LIFE IN THE GREAT CITY, 1870, undated (Box 33, Folder 53)
    - Olmsted, Frederick L., "Public Parks and the Enlargement of Towns," American Social Science Association, 1870, undated (Box 33, Folder 54)
    - "Apartment Houses Practically Considered," PUTNAM'S MAGAZINE, new series, 1870, undated (Box 33, Folder 55)
    - Bowen, Francis, AMERICAN POLITICAL ECONOMY, 1870, On Growth of Cities, 1969 (Box 33, Folder 56)
    - Towle, George M., AMERICAN SOCIETY, 1870. The lure of the city., undated (Box 34, Folder 1)
      3 1142 04225076 4
    - Living Conditions of Poor, 1869-1872, undated (Box 34, Folder 2)
    - Lure of the Big City, MILWAUKEE SENTINEL, 1871, undated (Box 34, Folder 3)
    - The Cityward Trend in Europe and America, Articles in EVERY SATURDAY, 1870, 1871, undated (Box 34, Folder 4)
    - Kip, Leonard, "The Building of Our Building of Our Cities," HOURS AT HOME, 1870, undated (Box 34, Folder 5)
    - City on Plains, Cheyenne, Wyo., 1870, undated (Box 34, Folder 6)
    - Trend to Large Cities, Statistics, 1870-1950, undated (Box 34, Folder 7)
    - Broadway, Changes by 1870, undated (Box 34, Folder 8)
    - Nordhoff, Charles, "Misgovernment of New York," NORTH AMERICAN REVIEW, 1871, undated (Box 34, Folder 9)
    - Sturgis, Russell, Jr., "Modern Architecture" (city), NORTH AMERICAN REVIEW, 1871, undated (Box 34, Folder 10)
    - Articles in NATION condemning "boss government," 1871-1875, undated (Box 34, Folder 11)
    - Bellows, Henry W., "The Townward Tendency," in THE CITY, I (1872), 36-40., undated (Box 34, Folder 12)
    - Wright, Robert M., DODGE CITY [date?], 1872, ff., undated (Box 34, Folder 13)
    - Opera and Symphony, 1872, undated (Box 34, Folder 14)
    - Attitude toward Life in Suburbs, NEW YORK TIMES, Apr. 14, 1872, undated (Box 34, Folder 15)
    - Stevens, Paran; died, Apr. 26, 1872, undated (Box 34, Folder 16)
    - Ratzel, Friedrich, STADTE UND CULTURBILDER AUS NORDAMERIKA (1873-1874; pub'd, 1876), undated (Box 34, Folder 17)
    - Census, efforts of to determine number of "urban dwellers" at decennial periods, ff. 1874, undated (Box 34, Folder 18)
    - Association for Improving Condition of Poor, ANNUAL REPORT, 1874, undated (Box 34, Folder 19)
    - Spencer, Edward, Permanence of drift to city, 1874, undated (Box 34, Folder 20)
    - Adams, Charles F., NORTH AMERICAN REVIEW, 1874-1876, undated (Box 34, Folder 21)
    - Indianapolis, Promotion of, 1874, 1889, undated (Box 34, Folder 22)
    - THE SPIDER AND THE FLY, Prostitution in New York City, 1875, undated (Box 34, Folder 23)
    - Webb, Walter Prescott, Towns as temporary railheads on plains, 1875, undated (Box 34, Folder 24)
    - Hatton, Joseph, TO-DAY IN AMERICA (1881), Observation of, 1876, 1880, undated (Box 34, Folder 25)
    - Olmsted, F. L., Urban Drift in U.S., 1877, undated (Box 34, Folder 26)
    - Magie, B. C., "Growth of Cities," SCRIBNER'S MONTHLY, XV (1877-78), Recognition of urban change, undated (Box 34, Folder 27)
    - Parkman, Francis, Cities and Government Corruption, 1878, undated (Box 34, Folder 28)
    - Campbell, Sir George, Pattern of American Towns, 1878, undated (Box 34, Folder 29)
    - Ingersoll, Ernest, "Atlanta," HARPER'S NEW MONTHLY MAGAZINE, 1879-1880, undated (Box 34, Folder 30)
    - Census of 1880, REPORT ON SOCIAL STATISTICS OF CITIES, undated (Box 34, Folder 31)
    - Census of 1880, Progress of Cities of Western U.S., undated (Box 34, Folder 32)
    - Hayes, A. A., "The Metropolis of the Prairies" (Chicago), 1880, undated (Box 34, Folder 33)
    - Wabash, Indiana, Electric streetlights, 1880, undated (Box 34, Folder 34)
    - Gladden, Washington, "The Disadvantages of City Boys," 1880, undated (Box 34, Folder 35)
    - Muller, G. G., "The City of Pittsburgh," 1880, undated (Box 34, Folder 36)
    - Ingersoll, Ernest, "Milwaukee," HARPER'S NEW MONTHLY MAGAZINE, LXIII (1880-81), undated (Box 34, Folder 37)
    - Bryce, James, AMERICAN COMMONWEALTH, "Uniformity of American Life," 1880's, undated (Box 34, Folder 38)
    - Bryce, James, AMERICAN COMMONWEALTH, "Government of Cities," 1880's, undated (Box 34, Folder 39)
    - [Shapley, Rufus E.], SOLID FOR MULHOOLY: A SKETCH OF MUNICIPAL POLITICS UNDER THE LEADERS OF THE RING AND THE BOSS (1881), undated (Box 34, Folder 40)
    - Electric Light and Power, Reaction to, 1881, undated (Box 34, Folder 41)
    - [Anon.], "City Life in the United States," CONTEMPORARY REVIEW, 1881, undated (Box 34, Folder 42)
    - Freeman, Edward A., SOME IMPRESSIONS OF THE UNITED STATES. Trip, 1881; published, 1883., undated (Box 34, Folder 43)
    - Whitman, Walt, "Give Me the Splendid Silent Sun," City and Country, 1881, undated (Box 34, Folder 44)
    - James, Henry, WASHINGTON SQUARE; describes Washington Square, of 1835, published, 1881, undated (Box 34, Folder 45)
    - Lathrop, G. P., "A Clever Town Built by Quakers" (Philadelphia), HARPER'S NEW MONTHLY MAGAZINE, LXIV (1881-82), undated (Box 34, Folder 46)
    - Kennedy, W. S., "The Vertical Railway," HARPER'S NEW MONTHLY MAGAZINE, LXV (1882), undated (Box 34, Folder 47)
    - Bishop, Wm. H., "San Francisco," HARPER'S NEW MONTHLY MAGAZINE, LXVI (1882-83), undated (Box 34, Folder 48)
    - Bishop, Wm. H., "Southern California" (Los Angeles), HARPER'S NEW MONTHLY MAGAZINE, LXVI (1882-83), undated (Box 34, Folder 49)
    - Bishop, Wm. H., "St. Louis," HARPER'S NEW MONTHLY MAGAZINE, LXXVIII (1883-84), undated (Box 34, Folder 50)
    - Fiske, John, "The Federal Union," HARPER'S NEW MONTHLY MAGAZINE, LXX (1884-85), undated (Box 34, Folder 51)
    - Carnegie, Andrew, TRIUMPHANT DEMOCRACY (1886), undated (Box 34, Folder 52)
    - Haymarket Affair, 1886, undated (Box 34, Folder 53)
    - LEND-A-HAND, I (May, 1886), City and Country, undated (Box 34, Folder 54)
    - Walling, George, RECOLLECTIONS OF A NEW YORK CHIEF OF POLICE, 1887, undated (Box 34, Folder 55)
    - Platt, Walter B., "Certain Injurious Influences of City Life and Their Removal," American Social Science Association, Sep. 7, 1887, undated (Box 34, Folder 56)
    - Warner, Charles D., "Studies of the Great West," HARPER'S NEW MONTHLY MAGAZINE, LXXVI (December, 1887-May, 1888), LXXVII (June-November, 1888), Minneapolis, St. Paul, Chicago, St. Louis, Kansas City, undated (Box 34, Folder 57)
    - Roberts, Edwards, "The City of Denver," HARPER'S NEW MONTHLY MAGAZINE, LXXVI (1887-88), undated (Box 34, Folder 58)
    - Hale, Edward E., "The Congestion of Cities," FORUM, IV (1888), undated (Box 34, Folder 59)
    - Spearman, Frank H., "The Great American Desert," HARPER'S NEW MONTHLY MAGAZINE (1888), Smaller cities of the Plains, undated (Box 34, Folder 60)
    - Trolleys, Development of (Richmond, Va.), ca. 1888, undated (Box 34, Folder 61)
    - MacKenzie, J. S., "Sociological Impact of Growth of Large Cities," Lecture, 1889, undated (Box 34, Folder 62)
    - Guthrie, Oklahoma, Founding of, in HARPER'S WEEKLY, May 18, 1889, undated (Box 34, Folder 63)
    - Pull of the City, "Editor's Easy Chair," HARPER'S NEW MONTHLY MAGAZINE, 1889, undated (Box 34, Folder 64)
    - Habberton, John, OUR COUNTRY'S FUTURE, 1889, undated (Box 34, Folder 65)
    - Low, Seth, Provision of Gas; Problems of Cities, 1889, undated (Box 34, Folder 66)